Okay.
In this lecture I'm
going to talk about overlay VPN networks.
Basically a comparison
between a self-hosted one and one
that is a SaaS provider.
Here is a SaaS provider of these,
VPN networks.
The architectures are very similar.
One is hosted by yourself
and one is hosted up in the cloud.
All right.
So first off, an introduction
to what is an overlay VPN.
So they're virtual networks
that sit on top of physical networks
that allow me to connect multiple devices
that are across
different physical networks
all into one network.
That appears to be the same.
So it handles all the connections,
it handles encryption,
it handles Nat traversal, hole
punching to relay.
So it creates his virtual subnet
over the top of all these other subnets
that, could be involved,
even doing it dynamically.
For example, I've got a lab here at home.
I have a bunch of machines on
my network there.
When I travel, my laptops can connect to,
that network and be part of that network
in a Docker, a swarm.
So a very easily I can act no matter where
I'm at in the world, I can connect
to my, devices here at home
and act like I'm all on the same network.
Very cool. Very simple to do.
The core components in, these,
in this technology,
the design pattern is a control plane.
And the data plane,
the control plane is managing,
which nodes are involved
in, the network and handles,
all the key policies, controller routing,
all that stuff happens.
Or, happens, in there, in the control
plane and head
scale, it's open source is called,
tail scale control server.
And in zero tier it's cloud hosted.
And or you can self-hosted
the controller yourself.
But you're going to hear this term
software defined network controller.
That's the thing
that's making sure that I have
this virtual network
that's been established.
The data plane is the thing
that's actually moving the data
between the different nodes inside, your,
virtual network, right.
For that encrypted tunnels
and things like that.
Wire guard is used, for,
head scale and tail scale
and a custom
UDP, TCP is used for zero tier, right.
And there's a lot of other, tools
that are out there that can be used
for the similar things, but for these two,
that's what that's what we have.
Okay.
Core, components and terminology.
Our network policies, for example.
So I've got my virtual subnet,
I've got all the same things that I would
normally have in a normal subnet
as far as flow control
and things like that.
I can still have
with these virtual subnets as well.
Okay.
All right. Let's take a look
at the architecture real quick.
So I could have, for example,
a bunch of edge nodes.
And I can have two different cloud
regions up here if I'm doing everything
through my virtual overlay Vpm my
right, I can have that control plane
sitting there, whether it's head scale
or zero terror controller,
and all the nodes know how to access that,
control plane, right?
That overlay, VPN network,
it just needs you
need some way of getting access to that.
Well, that means I might have
a single point of failure here.
So if I'm using, zero tier
controller, for example,
zero tier
controller, is highly redundant.
If I'm doing head scale, doing my own,
I need to make sure that if I need
this high availability,
that I have this, set up appropriately
and that all of the nodes
can access that high
availability,
node that you're accessing.
This is primarily done through,
dynamic DNS and things like that,
so that I can make sure
that when I hit that name out there
in the internet that I'm hitting, I'm
hitting the right, controller
that I have out there.
Okay.
They also have it set up for security.
So I'm passing secure keys.
So not anyone's attaching to my controller
and joining my network
and things like that.
That would be really
bad if, if we did that.
All right.
So quick setup on this.
You can deploy head scale
and a Docker container on on a device.
Make sure remember
your controller needs to be accessible
by all of the different, hosts out there.
So you need this on an IP address
that is kind of in that in the open.
And you can set up a DNS
so that you can point to that.
Right. That's the easiest thing to do.
You'll need a small database like SQLite
or PostgreSQL, at scale
has a Docker compose that you can just run
and everything's up and running.
I'm pretty. Pretty easily. Right.
And there's also, tail scale,
where you can run this,
bare metal if you need to as well.
Then done a good job at make this really
easy to, set up and configure.
All right.
For zero tier architecture,
you've got a zero tier controller
that's out there,
and you can sign up on their website.
Zero tier.
You can sign up,
create your own little network up there.
And then all you have to do is install
the zero tier,
client onto all your machines,
and you're off to the races
and you can connect in it.
It forms everything
that you need to with add scale.
You have to install an agent
on all the nodes as well,
so that it knows how to connect up
to, your network controller.
Right.
So let's take a look at,
just a quick, comparative,
analysis between spinning it up yourself.
Right. There's
no cost to head scale and tail scale.
You have to control it.
If you're not good at doing high
availability, and managing it yourself,
then you probably want to go to zero tier
because that's managed for you.
And it's free,
but they have paid versions as well.
If you're moving a lot of data
through things
or have a lot of nodes that maybe you want
to, you want to do that.
The operational overhead on tail scale
and head scale is not too high by itself,
but there's a lot more flexibility,
that you can do there.
So I mean, there's
there's some things that,
if you're a good sysadmin, hand scale down
scales, a good way to go if you like.
Zero tier. Great.
Great product out there.
Free for limited amount. Right.
There's some flexibility there,
but overall
it does a great job
and is totally managed.
Or you can self-hosted your own
controller, from zero tier as well.
But you might as well
just go with head scale. In that case.
All right.
I've already mentioned this before.
High availability and security are key,
key management.
You want to make sure that you're
rotating your control plane,
certs and and keys
don't put forever on your keys.
You got to come up with a strategy
on how you're going to rotate those keys.
Periodically.
Make sure that, you,
set up
least privileged access across your notes.
Don't make them wide open.
And to make things highly available,
for your head
skill, you'll need multiple instances
with a shared database.
And you need a dynamic, DNS so that,
if one of your nodes goes down, hey,
it'll reroute to to the other node.
No problem. Right.
Zero tier already handles
high availability for you.
If you're using the managed service.
All right.
Lots of use cases for this,
remote developer connectivity.
I use it because I've got my machines
where I want to do some heavy work,
but hey, maybe I'm doing interactive
work on my edge device, my laptop.
And I go, all right,
this is ready to be, you
know, chunked on by my micro data center
that I have here.
I hit a button, I'm on the same network
and boom, it does all the work remotely.
So this gives me that edge to cloud.
Concept that I, that I've built,
in my own little AI data center.
If I want to expand my network
into a cloud service provider,
I could very easily spin up some instances
in the cloud, add them to my virtual
network, add them to my cluster,
my Docker Swarm or Kubernetes cluster.
And I'm off to I'm off to the races.
So really easy.
Use case to do this with.
All right best practices.
Multi-level, multi-factor
authentication is a must.
Rotate those, security keys,
make sure you have high availability.
And fail failover regularly
to make sure everything's working.
Hopefully,
when you're not really needing it.
Do those fail,
make sure things are working,
monitor your latency and throughput,
and relay usage through all this
and plan for,
non-overlapping virtual subnets.
You know, watch out
when you're defining your subnets.
You can set up multiple of these.
Not a problem.
You can have multiple, of these, networks
and multiple controllers.
There's been lots of research done on
where to place these controllers
for best speed.
If you're worried about speed,
there's lots of papers and research
you can go and do out there
on, software defined network
controller placement,
which is totally awesome.
And you can get a PhD in that if you
if you want.
That's, how much research
is being done in that space.